Guide to the Laura Bryant papers, [ca. 1891]-1961.
Bryant, Laura papers, [ca. 1891]-1961.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Laura Bryant papers, [ca. 1891]-1961.
2112
Laura. Bryant
28.1 cubic ft.
Papers, correspondence, books, diaries, notebooks, scrapbooks, clippings, programs, photographs.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Papers include professional correspondence with colleagues, publishers, and others concerning textbooks; also, her teaching career in general.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
Music teacher.
Laura Bryant taught singing and music in the Ithaca, New York, public schools, 1906-1950.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Papers include professional correspondence with colleagues, publishers, and others concerning the textbooks on which she collaborated with Hollis Dann and later Katherine Knapp (Let's Read Music: 1949), conferences of music educators, and her teaching career in general; personal letters from former students, friends, and family; and diaries (incomplete run) and notebooks. Also, scrapbooks of press notices concerning her own activities and other clippings relating to former students, Cornell personalities, and numerous other persons and subjects; Ithaca High School concert programs (2 vols., 1901-50), Cornell Dramatic Club programs (1925+), and Cornell music programs (1915+); Ithaca High School Choral Club correspondence and newspaper clippings (1923-40), miscellaneous concert and theater programs (1903+), and verse and lyrics. Also, unmounted programs and scores from Cornell Music Festivals (1907-20); albums of photographs and picture postcards, as well as substantial numbers of loose photographs, postcards, musical scores, and clippings; student grade books and roll books, reports, bulletins, music teachers' magazines, and other publications, and miscellaneous materials relating to her teaching in Ithaca schools and in summer sessions at Cornell, San Francisco State College, Utah State Agricultural College, Louisiana State University, and elsewhere; items pertaining to the Bryant family and to Miss Bryant's study and early work in Indiana, and other items.
Includes correspondence from Karin White and other members of the White and Magill families.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Bryant, Laura.; Bryant family.; Dann, Hollis, 1861-1939.; Knapp, Katherine.; Magill family.; White family.; White, Karin.; Cornell Dramatic Club.; Ithaca High School. Choral Club.; Louisiana State University.; San Francisco State College.; Utah State University.
Subjects:
Music festivals.; Music--Instruction and study.; School music.; Singing--Instruction and study.; Women teachers.; Women--Diaries.; Music teachers.
Form and Genre Terms:
Albums.; Diaries.; Grade books.; Scores.; Photographs.; Scrapbooks.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
CONTAINER LIST
- Scrapbook containing press cuttings on old students, programs, etc. (Box 1)
- Scrapbook and two manilla folders containing correspondence in connection with Reader's Digest article, Sept. 1960 (Biography sketches on Laura Bryant) (Box 1)
- Scrapbook containing European picture postcards (Box 1)
- Photograph album (Box 1)
- Personal book plate (Box 1)
- Medal: Veterans of Foreign Wars Annual Citizanship Award, 1959 (Box 1)
- Passport (Box 1)
- Folio of Italian postcards (Box 1)
- Postcards and correspondence pertaining to Music Educators National Conference in Washington, 1961 (Box 1)
- Personal and professional letters up to 1960 (to and from students, old students, etc.) (Box 1)
- Package containing own school report ( 1900 ) and reports on students at Cornell summer session, 1920 (Box 1)
- Three students' notebooks, two for 1915, one for 1918 (Box 1)
- Personal letters from a woman-friend, 1913-1920 (Box 1)
- Records of Royalties received from sale of books (Box 1)
- Press cuttings in connection with members of Choral Club (Box 1)
- Personal letters, 1932-1936 (Box 2)
- Bundle of correspondence dated from 1926-1936 private and professional, it contains letters from Hollis Dan, the Dean of Cornell, various other universities (Box 2)
- Personal correspondence, 1923-1940 (Box 2)
- Personal correspondence, 1940-1948 (Box 2)
- Letters from Karin White and Beatrice Magill (Box 3)
- Twenty-two photographs (including one of Mrs. Andrew White) (Box 3)
- Letter from President of Cornell, 1924 (Box 3)
- Photograph of teachers, Laura Bryant in front row (Box 3)
- Postcard-sized photograph of Miss Bryant and Helen Magill White standing by fountain with pigeons in foreground; St. Mark's Square, Venice, 1921? (uncertain whether it is first or second trip to Europe) (Box 3)
- Interior photo of Basilica of San Francesco d'Assisi (Box 3)
- Photographic album of Rome (Box 4)
- Scores and programs from Cornell Music Festivals, 1907-1920 (Box 4)
- Miscellaneous scores and score collections (Box 4)
- Miscellaneous magazines, including "The Music Bulletin," Apr. 1926, which contains as article by Hollis Dan; a copy of "American Education," June 1912, which contains an article by Frank Boynton, then Ithaca Superintendent of Schools (Box 4)
- Picture postcards (Box 4)
- Diary, June 1905-Jan. 1906 (Box 4)
- Eight packets of Christmas cards (Box 4)
- Miscellaneous correspondence and photographs (Box 4)
- Program for dedication of Anabel Taylor Hall, 1952 (Box 4)
- Press cuttings pertaining to own graduation and photogrpah (Box 4)
- Copy of "As You Like It" (Box 4)
- Indiana State University Commencement Week program, 1949, and B.A. diploma (Box 4)
- Cards and correspondence, labelled "Guerlac," dated between 1953 and 1954 (Box 4)
- Picture postcard album (Box 5)
- School registers, 1918-1932 (imcomplete) (Box 5)
- Copies of "Opera News," Oct. 1940-Mar. 1941 (Box 5)
- Notebook on voice classification (Box 5)
- Two volumes of music (Box 5)
- Bundle of single scores (Box 5)
- Miscellaneous music teachers' magazines, 1930-1936 (Box 5)
- Two bundles of Christmas cards (Box 6)
- Scrapbook containing programs from Ithaca High School concerts, May 1934-May 1950 (Box 6)
- Two scrapbooks containing theatre programs; 1907-1923, 1931-1952 (Box 6)
- Miscellaneous concert programs, 1921 (Box 6)
- Scrapbook dated 1923, "Choral Club Volume II," includes letters and press cuttings to 1940 (Box 6)
- Scrapbook containing verse and lyrics (Box 6)
- Scrapbook containing programs of local concerts, 1903-1915 (Box 6)
- Scrapbook containing programs of general nature, 1913-1925 (Box 6)
- Scrapbook containing press cuttings, chiefly pertaining to Cornell personalities and self, from 1924 (Box 6)
- Scrapbook containing press cuttings of old pupils, 1940- (Box 7)
- Scrapbook containing concert programs, 1925- (Box 7)
- Scrapbook containing Cornell Dramatic Club programs, 1925- (Box 7)
- Scrapbook containing Ithaca High School programs, 1901-1933 (Box 7)
- Two scrapbooks containing Cornell Music programs, 1915- (Box 7)
- Scrapbook containing theatre programs, 1920-1928 (Box 7)
- Biography of Jenny McGraw Fiske (Box 7)
- Book: "Your Boy Samuel," a collection of Civil War Letters, private printing (Box 7)
- Church program, 1926 (Box 7)
- Diaries, Apr. 1938-, 1906, 1952 (Box 7)
- Leather folder containing photographs of Hollis Dann (Box 7)
- Postcards and correspondence from ex Ithaca High students, 1918 (Box 7)
- Copies of "Opera News" (Box 7)
- Envelope containing "Rare Christmas Cards" (Box 7)
- Misc. magazines, 1957 (Box 7)
- Letters and cards, 1941-1954, personal (Box 7)
- Pamphlet "44 Organ Recitals," Cornell Press, 1915 (Box 7)
- Picture scraps (from Christmas cards) (Box 7)
- Letters and Christmas cards around 1958 (Box 7)
- Press cuttings, mostly Cornell personalities, 1929- (Box 7)
- Miscellaneous European and American postcards, 1923- (including one to Mrs. Andrew White) (Box 8)
- 48 copies of "Opera News," 1946- (Box 8)
- Cuttings from "The New York State School Music News," Feb. 1959 (about her) (Box 8)
- Album of Thanksgiving Day concert photographs, 1958 (Box 8)
- Membership card N.Y. State School Music Association, 1959-1960 (Box 8)
- Typed pamphlet issued by Metropolitan Opera Guild, Mar. 1960 (Box 8)
- Calendar, 1911 (Box 8)
- Guide to Munich (labelled "Mrs. White") (Box 8)
- Edinburgh Festival guide, 1919 (Box 8)
- Diploma, "National Education Association" as an active member for life, 1927 (Box 8)
- Cornell University Music Review, 1959 (Box 8)
- Annual Reports of Ithaca Schools Music, 1926 (Box 8)
- Correspondence and instructions for a "Specialist in Physical Development" re prevention of sagging face muscle, 1918 (Box 8)
- "Music Bulletin," Mar. 1961 (mention of Ithaca High) (Box 8)
- Letters pertaining to 1945 reunion (Box 8)
- Personal and professional correspondence, 1944-1949 (Box 8)
- Cutting from "School and Society," Apr. 1935 L.B. mentioned) (Box 8)
- Letters from old students, 1943- (Box 8)
- European postcards, maps, etc. (Box 8)
- Postcards, programs, etc., from Munich festival, 1928 (Box 8)
- Letters from Valerai (?), 1921-1925 (Box 8)
- Envelope labelled "Hollis Dann" containing pince-nez (Box 8)
- Six folders containing miscellaneous professional and personal correspondence, 1928- (Box 9)
- Box file containing miscellaneous professional and personal correspondence, 1924- (Box 9)
- Box file containing miscellaneous personal correspondence, 1929-1939 (Clare Kimmel) (Box 9)
- Box file containing correspondence pertaining to her books, 1926-1935, with American Book Co. (Box 9)
- Christmas cards (Box 10)
- Miscellaneous notebooks and diaries, 1896 (Box 10)
- Photographs (Box 10)
- Tin box containing autographs, press cuttings, 1912 Glee Club (Box 10)
- Press clippings of general nature (Box 10)
- Program (2) of Eastern Music Supervisor's Conference, 1935 (L.B. President) (Box 10)
- File, "Dr. Dann," contains professional circulars, 1928-1930 (Box 10)
- Christmas cards (Box 11)
- Photographs (Box 11)
- Theatre stubs (Box 11)
- Scrap for pictorial scrapbook (Box 12)
- London "Evening Standard," Aug. 1921 (Box 12)
- "Get Well" cards, 1937 (Box 12)
- Magazines, 1953, 1957, 1959, containing articles of personal (professional) interest (Box 12)
- Diary of second trip to Europe (Box 12)
- Miscellaneous personal and professional correspondence (Box 12)
- Christmas cards (Box 13)
- Two cardboard boxes containing photographs and greeting cards, 1953-1957 (Box 13)
- Notebooks and diaries, 1906-1907, 1910-1911 (Box 13)
- Five personal notebooks, 1896 (Box 13)
- Personal letters written from Europe, 1912 (unsigned) (Box 13)
- Bundle of letters wirtten from 1914-1919 by Hollis Dann (Box 13)
- Letters written to Indiana, 1901 (Box 13)
- Ithaca High School programs, 1916- (Box 13)
- Letters, photographs, etc., and obituary on William Ballard, 1952 (Box 13)
- Letters from Peter Edge, 1929- (Box 13)
- "The Music Bulletin," article by Hollis Dann, Apr. 1926 (Box 13)
- Press cuttings, correspondence, pertaining to Glee Club, 1933 (Box 13)
- 2 files on Utah, programs etc., correspondence, 1952 (Box 13)
- Correspondence from servicemen, 1954 (Box 13)
- Miscellaneous records, factory pressings (Box 13)
- Ithaca High Spring Concerts, 1916- (Box 14)
- Copies of "Opera News," 1940- (Box 14)
- Miscellaneous programs (Box 14)
- Miscellaneous scores (Box 14)
- Letters from Willis Music Co. re "Lets Read Music" (Box 15)
- Miscellaneous letters, 1933-1945 (Box 15)
- Correspondence with Bob Treman, 1945- (Box 15)
- Correspondence with "The Instructor" re material, 1952- (Box 15)
- Envelope containing further letters from Hollis Dann, 1922-1923 (Box 15)
- Press cuttings of Royal Family (Box 15)
- Menus, recipes, etc. (Box 15)
- File labelled "Odds and Ends, Interesting" (Box 15)
- Photographs (Box 15)
- Miscellaneous scores (Box 15)
- Cornell Summer Sessions programs, 1916 (Box 15)
- Concert programs (Box 15)
- Duplicate of Teacher's Certificate (State of N.Y.) (Box 15)
- Photostat of final draft of Reader's Digest article prior to publication (Box 15)
- File labelled "Children's Poems," contains music (Box 15)
- Five copies of "Eastern School Music Herald," 1922-1923 (Box 15)
- Information on Bryant family (and photographs) (Box 15)
- Correspondence with Indiana Teacher's College (Box 15)
- Two folders containing scores (Box 15)
- Programs, including Cornell Glee Clubs, 1920 (Box 15)
- Christmas cards (Box 15)
- Personal receipts (money matters, Hollis Dann loan) (Box 15)
- Local theatre programs (Box 15)
- Photograph album, 1917 (Box 15)
- Copy of "Le Journal Musical Francais," Apr. 1955 (Box 15)
- Candy box containing letters from Hollis Dann, 1924 (Box 16)
- Letters of condolence on death of nephew John Kimmel, 1937 (Box 16)
- Correspondence with Kimmel family, 1928-1939 (Box 16)
- Correspodnence with John Kimmel's wife, 1937-1939 (Box 16)
- Final letters from Hollis Dann and letters from his family on his death (Box 16)
- Photographs (Box 16)
- Press cuttings (Box 16)
- Two files containing literary exercises (outline and crits.) (Box 16)
- Scroll containing a candle (Box 16)
- Box from Tiffany's containing personal correspondence, 1950- (Box 17)
- Miscellaneous correspondence, personal and professional, 1950- (Box 17)
- Miscellaneous journals (Box 17)
- Teacher's license, issued by the State of Indiana, Aug. 27, 1898, Feb. 27, 1897, May 27, 1899, Mar. 31, 1900 (Box 17)
- Reference, 1900 (Box 17)
- Glee Club programs, 1955 (Box 17)
- Correspondence from Dann's family, re commencing fund in his name, 1939- (Box 17)
- Cuttings from periodicals, 1931- (Box 17)
- Miscellaneous personal and professional correspondence, mainly 1940's-1950's (Box 18)
- Magazines, photographs, press cuttings 19-- (Box 18)
- Folder containing parts (Box 19)
- Local theatre programs (Box 19)
- Collection of early photographs (including one of a big concert, Laura Bryant and Hollis Dann prominent) (Box 19)
- Cornell calendars; 1914, 1916-1918, 1920-1921 (Box 19)
- Score from Cornell Music Festival, 1910 (Box 19)
- Gramophone records (Box 19)
- Miscellaneous personal and professional correspondence (Box 19)
- Professional letters, 1926-1940's, including L.B.'s carbons (Box 20)
- Several files of personal correspondence, filed under name of writer, 1930- (Box 20)
- Cornell Summer Schools programs (Box 20)
- Louisianna correspodnence, 1940 (Box 20)
- Drawing pads (Indiana) (Box 20)
- Indiana College mag. (Box 20)
- Correspondence with "The Instructor," 1950 (Box 20)
- Roosevelt press cuttings (Box 21)
- Christmas cards (Box 21)
- Letters, etc., from Bruce Boyee, 1956 (Box 21)
- M.E.N.C. programs, 1920-1950's (Box 21)
- Papers (speeches?) on the tuition of singing (Box 21)
- Correspondence, personal and professional, on retirement (Box 21)
- Photo album, 1890's? (Box 22)
- Fontainbleau programs, 1921- (Box 22)
- Teaching notebook (Box 22)
- Cornell calendar, 1924 (Box 22)
- Personal correspondence (Clare Kimmel), 1921-1925 (Box 22)
- General personal correspondence, 1905 (Box 22)
- Ceneral correspondence, 1924- (Box 22)
- Music conferences, correspondence, cuttings, etc., 1935 (Box 23)
- Copies of "Opera News," early 1950's (Box 24)
- Programs (Box 24)
- Miscellaneous journals, early 1950's (Box 24)
- Song book dated Apr. 6, 1896 (Box 25)
- Primer, simple sclaes by Hollis Dann (Box 25)
- Primer, second year music by Hollis Dann (Box 25)
- Score of "The Children's Crusade" (Box 25)
- Book of Anthems from Indiana State School, 1900 (Box 25)
- Professional and personal correspondence, 1927- (Box 25)
- Professional and personal correspondence, 1927- (Box 25)
- Correspondence and mementos of John Kimmel, 1914 (Box 25)
- Various scores, music manuals (Box 26)
- Copies of her books (Box 26)
  "Songs for Christmas," "Christmas Carols," "Lets Read Music," Lets Read More Music," "Sentence Songs for Little Singers," "Songs for Children"
- Diaries for 1946, 1956 (part), 1948, 1954, 1955 (Box 26)
- Sage Chapel Programs (Box 26)
- Christmas cards (Box 27)
- Photographs, teaching small children and alone (Box 28)
- Chorus roll for 1947 (Box 28)
- Choral Club roll for 1912-1948 (Box 28)
- Glee Club roll for 1906-1945 (Box 28)
- Arrangements for boys' choir concert, 1923-1929 (Box 28)
- Scrapbook conatining bound copies of programs, inscription on cover "Thanksgiving Concert" 1951 (Box 28)
- Utah register 1952 (Box 28)
- Diary, 1957 (Box 28)
- MENC folder containing correspondence (Box 28)
- Register, 1943 (Box 28)
- Address books (Box 28)
- Roll book, Baptist Church choir (Box 28)
- Notebook with names of Thanksgiving Reunion patronesses (2) (Box 28)
- Diary from Western College, 1947 (Box 28)
- Alumni Glee Club address book (Box 28)
- Correspondence, 1950's (Box 28)
- Scrapbook with further correspondence and lyrics (Box 28)
- Notebook beginning in 1898, with records of singers (Box 28)
- Registers, 1939, 1944-1945 (Box 28)
- Files and publications largely relating to music education (Box 29)
- Scrolls (Box 30)
  "more than 40 years" given and signed by Ithacans
  Indiana State Normal School Graduation Certificate, 1900
  Indiana State Normal School Diploma, 1902
  New School of Methods in Public School Music Certificate, 1907
- In manuscript file, Box 44 - 2 letters from Hugh Troy, Avery Road, Garrison, N.Y. dated, Oct. 20, 1948 each containing poems labeled copy for Laura Bryant; other letters and photos (Box 44)